<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Caveat for the Protestant clergy, or, A true account of the sufferings of the English clergy upon restitution of popery in the days of Queen Mary</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1671</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 28 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A39172</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E45</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R19703</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12400012</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12400012</idno>
            <idno type="VID">61251</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A39172)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 61251)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 275:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Caveat for the Protestant clergy, or, A true account of the sufferings of the English clergy upon restitution of popery in the days of Queen Mary</title>
                  <author>Y. E.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,]</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[S.l. :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1671.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed: Y.E.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Church history --  16th century.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Mary I, 1553-1558.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:61251:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A CAVEAT For the PROTESTANT CLERGY.</p>
            <p>Or, A TRUE ACCOUNT of the Sufferings of the ENGLISH CLERGY upon the Reſtitution of POPERY in the days of QUEEN <hi>MARY.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Virgilio Malvezzi</hi> in his <hi>Tarquin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The calamity of <hi>others</hi> may be a Leſſon to <hi>you:</hi> 'tis true, the good which is learned by what befalls <hi>ones ſelf,</hi> is counterpoiſed by diſaſters: he knows much, to whom much hath befallen; But who can learn by <hi>another mans harm;</hi> Say he be leſs <hi>wiſe,</hi> he is for certain more fortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate.</p>
            <p>Printed <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1671.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="publisher_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:61251:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:61251:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>The</hi> Publiſher <hi>to the</hi> Proteſtant Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Letter was ſent to a <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of Quality,</hi> whoſe <hi>Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> and <hi>Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence</hi> are ſuch, that, but to <hi>know him,</hi> and that <hi>He re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commended it to the Preſs,</hi> were enough to <hi>endear</hi> it to the peruſal of any Man. But neither have I power to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover him that approved it;
<pb facs="tcp:61251:3"/>nor doth the <hi>Author</hi> deſire the World ſhould know what <hi>he thinks upon,</hi> or <hi>writes to his friends:</hi> He is confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent <hi>this Age</hi> is ſo <hi>ſupinely negligent,</hi> and <hi>ignorant,</hi> that all this will paſs for a <hi>Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomer Dream,</hi> or ſome <hi>old fooliſh ſtory,</hi> in the <hi>know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge</hi> whereof <hi>this Generation</hi> is not concerned. But yet it is moſt certain, that they who are acquainted with the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings of the <hi>Papiſts</hi> in <hi>Auſtria, Bohemia,</hi> or <hi>France,</hi> will think what <hi>He writes</hi> to be <hi>probable.</hi> They who ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine things further, will find <hi>all to be exactly true:</hi> And they who <hi>by comparing paſt
<pb facs="tcp:61251:3"/>and preſent times,</hi> take a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the <hi>condition of our Affairs,</hi> will think the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lication <hi>to be neceſſary:</hi> How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, there is no hurt in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>cautilous;</hi> and many e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vents happen in the World that were as remote from the aprehenſion of them that ſuffer under them, as what the moſt <hi>jealous heads</hi> are perplexed at now in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land:</hi> The Reading hereof will not take up <hi>much</hi> of that <hi>time</hi> which is now the <hi>leaſt valued</hi> thing in this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and 'twill be no <hi>evil effect,</hi> if the conſideration hereof bring into any one's mind that Petition in the
<pb facs="tcp:61251:4"/>Lords Prayer, <hi>Lead us not into Temptation, but deliver us from evil,</hi> with which I conclude.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:61251:4"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Honoured Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Eaſt you ſhould inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pret my long <hi>ſilence</hi> to be a relinquiſhing of that <hi>Friendſhip</hi> which I have vowed unto <hi>You,</hi> I again renew that Corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondence which hath been ſo many Months diſcontinued: And becauſe you expect from me ſomewhat more than <hi>Ceremony</hi> and <hi>Complement,</hi> I ſhall here repreſent unto you an Account of the <hi>Condition</hi> of the <hi>Clergy</hi> under that revo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution in the Reign of Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> when <hi>Popery</hi> was re-eſtabliſhed. It is well known how that <hi>Queen</hi> was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moted to the <hi>Crown</hi> by the <hi>ſole aid</hi> and aſſiſtance of the <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> who flock'd unto her in <hi>Suffolk,</hi> and offered to ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard their Lives and Fortunes in her defence againſt the Lady <hi>Jane,</hi> who was proclaimed <hi>Queen,</hi> and abetted by the <hi>Nobility.</hi> 'Tis known that <hi>She</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:61251:5"/>unto the <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> that She would make no alteration in the <hi>eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed Religion:</hi> and this <hi>She</hi> did ſo <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly</hi> avow, that none misdoubted <hi>her Reality.</hi> But after <hi>She</hi> was once ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced into the <hi>Throne,</hi> and had poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed her ſelf of the <hi>Regal Power,</hi> She vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olated all thoſe <hi>Promiſes,</hi> and being put in mind thereof, anſwered, <hi>Foraſmuch as you being but Members deſire to rule your Head,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts &amp; Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, p. 1279</note> 
               <hi>you ſhall one day percieve that Members muſt obey their Head, and not look to bear rule over the ſame.</hi> And to terrify others from importuning her with ſollicitations <hi>of that nature,</hi> a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Gentleman named M. <hi>Dob,</hi> dwelling about <hi>Windam</hi> ſide, for the ſame cauſe, that is, for advertiſing her by humble requeſt of <hi>her Promiſe,</hi> was puniſhed by being ſet three ſeveral times <hi>in the Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lory.</hi> At firſt <hi>She</hi> made alteration in the <hi>Church,</hi> but aſſumed the Practice of <hi>her Religion,</hi> as ſhe allowed unto others the <hi>uſe of theirs:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ibid. p. 1281.</note> She declared no more by <hi>Proclamation,</hi> then teat being ſettled in the <hi>Throne</hi> ſhe could not hide that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion which God and the World knew <hi>She</hi> had ever profeſs'd from her infancy: which ſhe was minded to obſerve and maintain <hi>for her ſelf,</hi> during her time: and would be glad the ſame were of all
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:61251:5"/>her Subjects quietly and charitably em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced. Yet <hi>ſhe</hi> doth ſignify unto all her Majeſties loving Subjects, that of her moſt gracious diſpoſition and cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mency, her Highneſs mindeth not to <hi>compell</hi> any her ſaid Subjects <hi>thereunto,</hi> until ſuch time as further order by <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon conſent,</hi> may be taken therein. Forbidding nevertheleſs all her Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of all degrees, at their perils, to move Seditions, or ſtir unquietneſs in her People by interpreting the <hi>Laws of the Realm,</hi> after their Brains and Fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, but quietly continue for the time, till (as before ſaid) further order may be taken; and therefore willeth, and ſtraightly chargeth and commandeth all her ſaid good loving Subjects to live together in quiet ſort and Chriſtian charity, leaving thoſe <hi>new-found deviliſh terms</hi> of <hi>Papiſt</hi> and <hi>Heretick,</hi> or ſuch like, and applying their whole care, ſtudy, and travail to live in the fear of God, exerciſing their Converſations in ſuch a charitable and godly doing, as their Lives may indeed expreſſe that great hunger and thirſt of Gods Glory and Holy Word, which by raſh talk and words many have pretended: and in ſo doing they ſhall beſt pleaſe God, and live without the danger of the Laws,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:61251:6"/>and maintain the Tranquility of the Realm.</p>
            <p>After this, upon pretence of ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing all <hi>factious praying</hi> and <hi>Libels,</hi> She prohibited all univerſally (except in the Univerſities) <hi>to preach or teach any Scriptures, or any manner of points of Doctrine concerning Religion,</hi> unleſs they have her Majeſties ſpecial Licence for the ſame in <hi>writing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This <hi>Proclamation</hi> being made, ſhe proceeded to trouble ſuch <hi>Miniſters</hi> as did oppoſe the <hi>Popiſh Doctrines</hi> preached by Mr. <hi>Bourne:</hi> ſeveral were ſummon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed before the <hi>Council,</hi> and caſt into <hi>Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> who had either <hi>preached</hi> or <hi>talked</hi> againſt the Queen's proceedings.</p>
            <p>Divers Biſhops ſuſpended in the days of her Brother <hi>Edward,</hi> were reſtored, <hi>viz.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Heylin</hi> doth call him Biſhop <hi>Poinet;</hi> I know not <hi>why;</hi> for he writes his own name <hi>Poynett.</hi>
               </note> Dr. <hi>Gardiner</hi> to <hi>Wincheſter,</hi> and <hi>John Poynec</hi> put out; Dr. <hi>Bonner</hi> to <hi>London,</hi> and <hi>Nicholas Ridley</hi> confined; <hi>Joh. Day</hi> to <hi>Chicheſter,</hi> and <hi>J. Scory</hi> exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded; Dr. <hi>Torſtal</hi> to <hi>Durham;</hi> Dr. <hi>Heath</hi> to <hi>Worceſter, John Hooper</hi> excluded, and committed to the <hi>Fleet;</hi> Dr. <hi>Veſey</hi> to <hi>Exceſter;</hi> and <hi>Miles Coverdale</hi> caſhier'd. And in the beginning of the <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> before any Laws of K. <hi>Edward</hi> VI. were repealed, Mr. <hi>Harley</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Hereford,</hi> was excluded from the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:61251:6"/>
               <hi>Houſe of Peers</hi> for being married; and of thoſe which ſhould adhere to the <hi>Laws in being</hi> (till they were repealed) ſome were marked, and others preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly apprehended.</p>
            <p>The <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſities</hi> were ſeverely vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fited, and many either expell'd or forc'd to retire:<note place="margin">Acts &amp; Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, <hi>p.</hi> 1341.</note> in our Colledge of S. <hi>John</hi>'s in <hi>Cambridge,</hi> 24 places were vacuated; and no leſs miſerable was the ſtate of <hi>Oxford,</hi> by reaſon of the rigorous and ſtrict dealing of the <hi>Viſitors,</hi> that to ſet forward their <hi>Papiſtical</hi> proceedings, had no regard to the <hi>ingenious</hi> or <hi>learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our <hi>Records</hi> ſhew, that <hi>Five Biſhops,</hi> and <hi>twenty one Divines</hi> were <hi>put to death</hi> in thoſe days: But the particular uſage of the <hi>Clergy</hi> is not ſo related in any <hi>Chronicles</hi> I have yet ſeen,<note place="margin">It was Dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to K. <hi>Philip,</hi> and Q. <hi>Mary,</hi> and <hi>all</hi> the <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates</hi> in <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
               </note> as in a <hi>Defence of the Married Clergy,</hi> whoſe Author I know not; (my Book being imperfect) and becauſe I think it may be ſomewhat <hi>new</hi> unto <hi>you,</hi> as it was to me, I deſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the <hi>ſum</hi> of it for the Subject of this <hi>Letter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There were <hi>twelve or ſixteen thouſand</hi> Clergy-men turned out in thoſe days, at one time, and reduced to great po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty; this was done and executed to the uttermoſt, and againſt all <hi>Juſtice</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:61251:7"/>upon a number of them, even after the charge of the <hi>Cure</hi> ſerved, the <hi>Tenths</hi> and <hi>Subſidy</hi> paid,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>N.B.</hi> In this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation I gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally retain the <hi>Language,</hi> and even the <hi>Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graphy</hi> often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times of my Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor</note> and they at the point of receiving that which was before la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured for, and deſerved, all was ſnatch'd out of their mouths by <hi>preven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</hi> Some were <hi>deprived,</hi> and never <hi>convict,</hi> no never <hi>call'd.</hi> Some <hi>call'd,</hi> that were faſt lockt in Priſon, and yet ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs <hi>deprived</hi> immediately. Some <hi>deprived</hi> without the caſe of <hi>Marriage after Orders.</hi> Some induced to reſign upon promiſe of <hi>Penſion,</hi> and the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe never performed. Some ſo <hi>depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved,</hi> that they were ſpoiled of their wages, for which they had ſerved the laſt half year before, and not ten days before the receipt <hi>ſequeſtred from it.</hi> Some <hi>prevented</hi> from the half years re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipt, after charges of <hi>Tenths</hi> and <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidy</hi> paid; and yet not <hi>deprived</hi> till ſir weeks after. Nay, they ſtood charge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able in <hi>Law</hi> for their <hi>firſt Fruits,</hi> not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding their <hi>deprivation.</hi> Nor were they only <hi>divorced</hi> from their <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vings:</hi> But the Orders of <hi>Bonner</hi> are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant whereby they were appointed to bring their <hi>Wives</hi> within a Fortnight,<note place="margin">Acts &amp; Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, <hi>p.</hi> 1334.</note> that <hi>they</hi> might likewiſe be <hi>divorced from them</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:61251:7"/>
            <p>The <hi>Queens</hi> Articles ſent into <hi>every Dioceſs</hi> with Letters writ unto the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral reſpective <hi>Biſhops,</hi> were of the <hi>ſame import,</hi> though in <hi>ſome things</hi> bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>qualifyed,</hi> than thoſe that were to put them in <hi>execution</hi> would have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard unto: But 'tis no nnuſual thing in ſo <hi>great revolutions</hi> for the <hi>Inſtruments</hi> to exceed <hi>their Commiſsion;</hi> and to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply more with their <hi>private inſtructions</hi> or <hi>intentions,</hi> than the <hi>publick Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> of <hi>their Prince.</hi> Whatſoever there is of <hi>mitigation</hi> in them, was not taken notice of, but ſuch <hi>rigour</hi> practiſed, as I relate. The <hi>Articles</hi> relating to this <hi>Subject</hi> were.</p>
            <q>
               <p>That every Biſhop and his Officers,<note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Heylin</hi>'s Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation. <hi>Ann. Reg. Mar.</hi> 1. 1553</note> and all others having Eccleſiaſtical Jurisdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, proceeding ſummarily, and with all celerity and ſpeed, may, and ſhall deprive, or declare deprived, and remove according to their learning and diſcretion, all ſuch perſons from their Benifices and Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical Promotions, who contrary to the ſtate of their Order, and the laudible cuſtom of the Church, have married, and uſed Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men as their Wives, or otherwiſe notably and ſlanderouſly diſordered or abuſed themſelves, Sequeſtring alſo, during the ſaid Proceſs, the Fruits and Profits of the ſaid Beneſices and Eccloſiaſtical promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:61251:8"/>
               <p>That the ſaid Biſhop, and other Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons aforeſaid, do uſe more lenity and cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mency with ſuch as have married, whoſe Wives be dead, than with others whoſe <hi>Women</hi> do yet remain alive. And like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe ſuch Prieſts, as with the conſent of their Wives or <hi>Women,</hi> openly in the preſence of the Biſhop, do profeſs to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtain, to be uſed more favourable. In which caſe, after <hi>Pennauce effectually done,</hi> the Biſhop according to his diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and wiſdom, may upon juſt conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, receive and admit them again to their former adminiſtrations, ſo it be not in the ſame place, appointing them ſuch a portion to live upon, to be paid out of their Benifice, whereof they be deprived, by the diſcretion of the ſaid Biſhop, or his Officer, as he ſhall think may be ſpared of the ſame Benifice.</p>
               <p>That every Biſhop, and other Perſon aforeſaid, do fore-ſee that they ſuffer not any <hi>Religious</hi> Man, having <hi>ſolentnly profeſſed Chaſtity,,</hi> to continue with his <hi>Woman</hi> or Wife, but that all ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons after Deprivation of their Benefice, or Eccleſiaſtical Promotion, be alſo divor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced from his ſaid Woman, and due pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment otherwiſe taken for the Offence therein.</p>
            </q>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:61251:8"/>
            <p>In theſe <hi>Articles</hi> 'tis to be obſerved, that the <hi>Queen</hi> ſeems more inclined to call the <hi>Wives</hi> of the Married Clergy rather <hi>Women,</hi> than any <hi>other name:</hi> and matters were ſo ordered, that not only the <hi>Regular Clergy,</hi> which do <hi>vow Chaſtitie,</hi> but the <hi>Seculars,</hi> (who promiſe at <hi>their Ordination</hi> only <hi>caſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem colere &amp; docere;</hi> which was the <hi>old Form,</hi> and obligeth them <hi>directly</hi> no more to <hi>refrain Marriage,</hi> than to <hi>teach others ſo to do,</hi>) were divorced from their <hi>Wives,</hi> and deemed to have made a <hi>ſolemn profeſsion of Chaſtitie,</hi> according to thoſe Verſes,
<q>
                  <l>Ordo, Sacer, veſtis, profeſſio Religionis</l>
                  <l>Quae ſit facta palam factunt ſolemnia vota.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Marryed Clergy</hi> were in all places re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented as <hi>Lewd Fellows;</hi> Nay, it came to that paſs <hi>immediately,</hi> as that they were im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted ſuch an <hi>unworthy ſort of Men,</hi> that they ought not to be ſaid <hi>Ave</hi> unto in <hi>ſalutation:</hi> not fit to come to their <hi>Tables</hi> or <hi>Preſence,</hi> for diſteining their <hi>Holineſs</hi> and myſtical vows of <hi>Chaſtity.</hi> Whereas in truth the <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Prieſts</hi> of the <hi>Engliſh Church</hi> were never under any ſuch <hi>Vow,</hi> nor did our <hi>Pontifical</hi> oblige them to <hi>any ſuch thing:</hi> as Dr. <hi>Redman</hi> atteſted in the <hi>Convocation-houſe;</hi> profeſſing <hi>they were not bound by reaſon of any Vow, which (in as far as his Conſcience was the Prieſts in this Church of</hi> England <hi>do not make.</hi> But all <hi>Pleas</hi> were rejected; it was in vain for
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:61251:9"/>them to ſay <hi>they</hi> did nothing but what was warranted by the <hi>Laws of the Land,</hi> the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation,</hi> or <hi>Scripture,</hi> and <hi>Fathers:</hi> they were condemned for <hi>breach of Vows,</hi> as if they had been <hi>Ordained</hi> by <hi>Romiſh Poutifical</hi> and not that of <hi>England.</hi> The <hi>Popiſh Clergy</hi> told them, that upon the repealing of the <hi>Laws in being,</hi> the old <hi>Laws</hi> and <hi>Canons</hi> did <hi>ipſo facto</hi> take place, and oblige, though there was no <hi>expreſs Statute</hi> for it, and though the Queens <hi>Commiſsion</hi> was, that <hi>they ſhould proceed according to Learning and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion in this weighty matter: and that they ſhould not put any other Canons and Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Church in exerciſe, than ſuch as might ſtand with the Law of the Realm.</hi> Yet for all this grave and gracious Advertiſement, divers of the Officials proceeded ſo far a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Learning, diſcretion,</hi> and <hi>Laws of the Realm</hi> in moſt places, ſo that the poor Subjects and Oratours were far otherwiſe uſed than one would have imagined, <hi>conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering the truſt committed to them.</hi> In truth it appears that <hi>all Pleas</hi> were invalid againſt the <hi>Arbitrary</hi> proceedings of <hi>thoſe times;</hi> and whatever was alledged out of the <hi>Laws</hi> and <hi>Conſtitutions</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> though never ſo old, and made in the times of <hi>Popery,</hi> (and <hi>who is ſafe,</hi> if ſuch a defence be <hi>invalid:</hi>) were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feated by this general aſſertion of Dr. <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin,</hi> and others, that no <hi>Laws bind againſt the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:61251:9"/>Church,</hi> but are <hi>ipſo jure &amp; ipſo facto</hi> unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, void, and of none effect; That a <hi>parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Church, a little Member of the whole, cannot derogate the univerſal Law of the Church.</hi> They proceeded ſo far as to tell Men, that the <hi>Acts</hi> of K. <hi>Edward</hi> VI. did not take away the <hi>penalty of the Canon Laws:</hi> and interpreted that <hi>Act</hi> of Q. <hi>Mary,</hi> which <hi>bare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> repealed the <hi>Statutes</hi> of K. <hi>Edward,</hi> as it had <hi>annulled the Marriages of Prieſts.</hi> Nay, though there were a <hi>Statute</hi> in force then, made <hi>triceſimo ſecundo</hi> of <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth, that no <hi>Reſervation</hi> or <hi>Prohibition (Gods Law except) ſhall trouble or impeach any Marriage, without the ſaid Levitical Degrees: and that all ſuch be lawful perſons to contract, which be not prohibited by Gods Law to marry</hi> Yet did <hi>they</hi> proceed to annull the <hi>Marriages;</hi> and ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gued, that the <hi>Prieſts could take no advantages of the Law, any longer than it continued:</hi> and that the <hi>ancient Laws of the Church were never extinguiſhed, but only for a time ſhadowed, and brought aſleep.</hi> It was further argued by the <hi>married Clergy</hi> thus: <hi>But to return again to Dr.</hi> Martins <hi>aſſertion, wherein he defineth, that the</hi> Church-Canons be ready, watching ſtraightways to fall into mens necks, upon repeal of ſuch Statutes as kept them back: <hi>which he doth ſo boldly, that belike the wiſe and well learned Commiſsaries, in diverſe places, without further adviſement, taketh upon them
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:61251:10"/>wonderous ſtoutly, to ſeparate, not only</hi> Regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, <hi>but</hi> Seculars <hi>too, againſt their wills and conſents. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon which their doings, I would ask them a queſtion:</hi> How they <hi>can gloſe the words of K.</hi> Henries <hi>Statute in the</hi> XXVII. <hi>year of his Reign, where it is plainly decreed in Law, that</hi> all manner of Licenſes, Diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations and Faculties obtained of the Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> in matters not repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant or contrary to the holy Scriptures, and Laws of God, ſhall ſtand in full Authority and ſtrength, without any revocation or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal hereafter to be had of any ſuch Licence. <hi>And I know diverſe married Prieſts, which have ſuch</hi> Diſpenſations, <hi>ſome corroborated by the</hi> Kings Broad Seal, <hi>and ſome by the ſaid</hi> Arch-Biſhops Seal. <hi>I would fain learn, how they underſtand theſe</hi> weighty Laws <hi>of the Realm. Belike, as they have proceeded in</hi> Deprivations <hi>of many Men,</hi> never called, <hi>or</hi> cited, <hi>never</hi> convict, <hi>nor</hi> confeſſed; <hi>and ſome called on one day, and ſlat deprived on the next day, not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amining</hi> whether he were Secular <hi>or</hi> Regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, married before Orders, <hi>or</hi> after, <hi>without all manner of inquiſition: So belike they deſire to proceed in</hi> Separations, <hi>againſt both</hi> God's Law, <hi>and</hi> their own. <hi>And as for the</hi> Laws of the Realm, <hi>they make but</hi> waſhway <hi>of them, ſo little compting of them, that if a</hi> Lord <hi>ſhould ſee his</hi> Tenants <hi>in his</hi> Court-Baron <hi>ſo little re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard the</hi> by-Laws <hi>of his Courts, he would think
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:61251:10"/>them not unworthy, to looſe their</hi> Copies.— To this the only anſwer I can find, is, <hi>The marriages of the Clergy be ſo great offences, that they cannot be forgiven by no manner of means,</hi> no not by Chriſts Blood, <hi>but only by a Separation. And Dr.</hi> Martin <hi>ſaith further<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more, that Biſhops and Prieſts have ſo great de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formities and skars yet remaining in their Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies and Souls,</hi> for their old Inceſts, <hi>(as he calls them) that they cannot be mitigated by any gentle Medicine, Chriſtian Clemency, no not purged yet, nor ſufficiently puniſhed,</hi> with the deprivations of all their Livings, <hi>but muſt look for much more yet,</hi> Curſes, Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munications, Excoriations, Confiſcations, open Pennance, <hi>yea, the Devil, Hell, and all.</hi> — And Dr. <hi>Martin</hi> aſſures the <hi>Clergy</hi> that they were dealt with <hi>very favourably</hi> in being turned out of their <hi>Miniſtrations,</hi> and no further <hi>Penalties</hi> inflicted on them. 'Tis not to be denyed, but that <hi>after they were turned out of their Livings,</hi> the Church did mercifully open her lap to receive them into <hi>new Benefices</hi> and <hi>Livings,</hi> though they had loſt <hi>their old,</hi> where they had done coſt. But ſuch was the <hi>Churches merciful lap,</hi> in recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving her own begotten Children to <hi>mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration</hi> again, that yet firſt they muſt ſpeak their own ſhame in <hi>Bills of their Pennance,</hi> ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing againſt themſelves, moſt vilely &amp; ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully diſabling their credit and eſtimation
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:61251:11"/>for ever. They muſt profeſs an <hi>earneſt</hi> and <hi>hearty repentance of that foul ſin</hi> of Unchaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie by <hi>marrying,</hi> relinquiſh their <hi>Wives</hi> for the future, and bear ſuch a part in <hi>Proceſsion,</hi> as <hi>Jane Shore</hi> doth in the <hi>Puppet-Plays,</hi> car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying <hi>Tapers</hi> in their hands: I could wiſh all our <hi>Clergy</hi> would reſor to <hi>Bartholomew</hi> Fair, and behold <hi>that ſpectacle,</hi> and judge of that <hi>happy condition</hi> into which <hi>their ſupinity</hi> will precipitate them. Some did undergo it in the days of Q. <hi>Mary:</hi> and, <hi>Surely in ſome places the Churches mercy was ſo ſore extended, that whoſe Wives were two or three years paſt before departed, yet they could not be admitted again to miniſtration, but muſt do open Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, and go before the Croſs, without any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption or intreaty that could be made; and the parties ſuch as by whom the Commiſſaries themſelves could alledge not one point of diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty, or evil opinion in all their converſation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides forth. Shall Lay-men hereafter truſt well of the Churches Mercy, if they come within their claws, when the Clergy are thus dealt with? Of whom ſome diſſented in no Point at all from the Papiſts, but only in this fact, which the Law made them bold to adventure on.</hi>—Thus, Sir, were thoſe <hi>Clergy-men</hi> ſerved, who before <hi>that fatal change,</hi> were in as good and law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful poſſeſſion of their <hi>Wives</hi> and <hi>Livings,</hi> as any Subject ever ſhall have of <hi>any thing</hi> here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after. Nor is there any way for the <hi>preſent
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:61251:11"/>Clergy</hi> to avoid the <hi>like inveniencies</hi> ſhould <hi>ſuch a Revolution</hi> happen (from which the <hi>greateſt ſecurity</hi> we have, as to <hi>humane</hi> and <hi>Political</hi> Affairs, is the great <hi>Zeal</hi> which our <hi>Prince</hi> continues to ſhew for the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and that <hi>unqueſtionable unſhaken</hi> conſtancy with which <hi>His Maieſty</hi> perſiſted to be a <hi>Proteſtant</hi> during his Exile) except it be confeſſed that <hi>they are not in Orders,</hi> and that the <hi>Succeſsion</hi> did ceaſe in the Election of <hi>Matthew Parker</hi> to be Arch-biſhop of <hi>Canterbury:</hi> this is a thing the <hi>Papiſts</hi> do commonly ſay: and Dr. <hi>Champney</hi> hath writ a <hi>plauſible Book</hi> to prove it: and if it be true, that <hi>He</hi> which makes <hi>arbitrarily</hi> Biſhops in <hi>Greece,</hi> of <hi>Chalcedon, Corinth,</hi> &amp;c. hath or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained ſome for <hi>England,</hi> and <hi>Ireland;</hi> 'tis eafie to judge <hi>what courſes will be taken,</hi> ſhould <hi>Proteſtancy</hi> looſe its <hi>Legal force,</hi> and <hi>power.</hi> Perhaps you will ſay that <hi>ſuch a revo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution</hi> would endanger the <hi>Layety</hi> alſo, and bring the <hi>Crown of his Majeſty</hi> into Queſtion, whether it be <hi>feudatory,</hi> or <hi>no:</hi> 'tis true in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, that the <hi>Papiſts</hi> do now <hi>entitle</hi> ſome of <hi>their Clergy</hi> to our <hi>old Abbeys</hi> and <hi>Monaſteries;</hi> and in <hi>France</hi> there is a <hi>Nunnery</hi> that layes claim to <hi>Sion houſe,</hi> and they are called the <hi>Nuns of Sion.</hi> 'Tis moſt true that the <hi>Pope</hi> doth reckon upon our <hi>Kingdom</hi> as held in <hi>Fee</hi> of the <hi>Papacy,</hi> and to this purpoſe did <hi>Beller<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine</hi> produce unto K. <hi>James</hi> other Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:61251:12"/>than the <hi>Donation of Conſtantine.</hi> Bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> I am reſolved not to doubt the <hi>integrity</hi> or <hi>prudence</hi> of his Majeſty, or our <hi>Parliament;</hi> 'tis not to be doubted but the <hi>intellectuals</hi> of <hi>States-men</hi> are as elivated as their <hi>condition</hi> is above others, and their <hi>proſpect</hi> greater into Affairs: what paſſed in the days of Q. <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> and K. <hi>James</hi> is not effaced out of our knowledge: and 'tis only the intent of this <hi>Letter</hi> to acquaint you with <hi>the condition of the Proteſtant Clergy</hi> in the days of Queen <hi>Mary.</hi> Dr. <hi>Heylin</hi> hath not treated ſo fully of <hi>this matter</hi> as I have here: and I think it would be a <hi>ſeaſonable Work</hi> to publiſh Dr. <hi>Martin</hi>'s Book about the proceedings againſt the <hi>Clergy</hi> then; and the <hi>Defence of Prieſts Marriage,</hi> (which is the Book I follow, and 'tis a <hi>learned piece,</hi> written by ſome <hi>eminent</hi> Man, but mine is defective in the <hi>beginning,</hi> and wants a <hi>ſheet</hi> in the middle.) Nothing informs us ſo much as <hi>Hiſtory,</hi> and to be <hi>fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warned,</hi> is in a manner to be <hi>fore-armed.</hi> I am</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your moſt devoted Servant, <hi>Y. E.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:61251:12"/>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
